Guide to the Seattle Teachers' Association Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Seattle Teachers' Association records
1958-1969
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
1402
1402-001
Seattle Teachers' Association (Seattle, Wash.)
16.32 cubic feet (15 boxes)
Educational organization of Seattle, Washington
The Seattle Teachers’ Association or STA was formed with the 1958 merger of the Seattle Association of Classroom Teachers and the Seattle Grade Teachers’ Club. The plans for this unification had been in the works for nearly ten years, and it produced the largest schoolteacher organization in Washington State, with 2,500 members. The STA was formed to represent the collective bargaining rights of teachers in Seattle Public School District No. 1., with the objective of developing “public understanding of the objective of education, promote its goal, and encourage the professional growth of association members.” Over the years, the organization began to focus on the welfare of its members and became more strident in its advocacy efforts.
The STA was affiliated with the Washington Education Association (WEA) and the National Education Association (NEA).The STA also collaborated with the Local 609 and the Operating Engineers Union, two unions associated with building maintenance in Seattle Schools.
During much of the period covered by this collection, the STA had minimal bargaining and professional negotiating power. To gain leverage in this period, the STA used a variety of techniques: it pressured and courted individual local legislators, met with the school board and offered input, and commissioned and collected studies and reports to support the STA position. The STA also kept close ties to the WEA and NEA in this time period and used the resources and support of these larger, more established organizations. Much of the STA activities of this time period involved soliciting and sharing knowledge with the WEA, NEA, and other teacher organizations throughout the country. As a relatively new organization, the STA was mostly focused on accruing members and maintaining their participation. Therefore, much of the material in this collection deals with the day-to-day operations and organizing of the STA.
Yet at this time the STA did give attention to some specific issues. The STA was consistently concerned about issues of members’ salaries, rights, and employment, district funding, and school curriculum. Specific to the late 1950s and early 1960s, the STA particularly lobbied for teaching to be treated as a profession and, therefore, to be given the proper respect, resources, and salaries. The STA also supported local levies, appealings to voters and gain electoral support. This strategy was at its height in the early 1960s. At the same time, the STA argued that the levy system was only a band-aid and did not fundamentally address the salary issues. One other major issue of the time, particularly in the late 1960s, was the question of how to give a better education in Central Area schools, Washington Middle School, Meany Middle School, and Garfield High School. These schools suffered a variety of crises, particularly of student violence and protest, in the late 1960s. The STA was concerned with how to best aid the teachers in these schools, in giving them appropriate physical protection, emotional relief, and eventually alleviating the problems in the schools. Connected to this issue was that of school de-facto segregation, and the STA supported efforts to alleviate the racial segregation. Overall, the STA in this period was concerned largely with educator rights, but also with many related topics.
The STA began to take a more assertive tone during the later 1960s. For example, in 1967 president of the STA Pete Neuschwander declared that a proposed $15.7 million levy, the largest in Seattle history at the time, was “not enough.” 1 The STA also assisted with a football and cross country coaches’ strike in 1968 and began to threaten a teachers’ strike if the proposed 1968 levy did not pass. Some of this increased assertiveness may have been in response to pressure from the Seattle Federation of Teachers, or SFT. The SFT competed with the STA for membership and typically took a harder-line and more assertive action, like picketing a compromise in teachers’ wages in 1967.
Much of this assertiveness, however, was probably in response to gaining negotiation power. The STA worked with the WEA to pass the Professional Negotiations Act, or State of Washington Chapter 143 Law of 1965 (amended in 1969). STA President Wes Ruff hailed it as a great step, stating, “‘The Seattle School Board, without a doubt, is one of the finest in the state…. But there is a difference between us making a half-hour ‘presentation’ and actually hammering things out in real negotiations…. The board, the decision-maker, owes itself the opportunity to have conversations with the practitioners in the field, the educators with knity-gritty information.’” 2 This law furthered the impact of genuine educator input in district policy by granting certificated Seattle school district employees a representative body for the purpose of negotiating with the superintendent and school board. This legislation had a broader scope than wages, hours, and conditions of employment, as it allowed for educator input on such features as curriculum and textbook selection. According to the Professional Negotiations Act, the body that communicated with the school board was required to represent not solely teachers, but all certified personnel within the district except the superintendent. Therefore, the STA created the Seattle Alliance of Educators, or SAE, an umbrella organization that advocated on behalf of the Seattle Teachers’ Association, the Seattle Principals’ Association, the Seattle Administrative and Supervisory League. Membership was indirect, via enrollment in one of these constituent organizations. The requisite involvement of administrators and principals placed many of these employees into difficult positions, straddling the fence between their administrative roles and positions as employees and SAE members. By the mid-1970s, the administrators and principals had disbanded their organizations, and the SAE had very little actual administrative participation. In 1976, the SAE merged back into the STA, and an STA Bargaining Commission was formed to perform the duties of the SAE.
A large subgroup of this collection contains primarily WEA-produced materials. The WEA was formed “to promote the cause of education in the state of Washington.” It was affiliated with the NEA and the STA, but covered all teachers in the state. Many of these artifacts specifically deal with the WEA’s relationship with the STA, such as correspondence with STA leadership. For a history of the organization between 1970 and 1985, see the finding aid for the Seattle Education Association Records, 1958-1985.
Notes on Organizational History
1. “Record-Size School Levy to Be on Ballot,” Constantine Angelos Seattle Daily Times, September 21, 1967, p. 32.
2. “School Directors Fear Negotiations Act” Seattle Daily Times, November 18, 1965, p. 11.
This collection can be divided into several subgroups: constitution and by-laws, correspondence, minutes, financial information, reports, ephemera and miscellany, subject series, committee papers and minutes, and WEA materials. Correspondence is separated into “incoming” and “outgoing” and is in roughly chronological ordered by year, then in alphabetical order by sender or recipient within that year. The Subject Series is organized by topic, and topics are organized alphabetically. Much of the material in this subdivision is technically ephemera.
Correspondence, minutes, financial records, subject files. This collection contains several subgroups: constitution and by-laws, correspondence, minutes, financial information, reports, ephemera and miscellany, subject series, committee papers and minutes, and WEA materials. Materials in this collection range from 1953-1969.
Several copies of the STA constitution and by-laws are contained within this collection. This includes several incarnations and revisions of both. This collection also includes the constitution and by-laws of related organizations like the WEA.
The correspondence includes material from 1953 (addressed to the Seattle Association of Classroom Teachers), but then jumps to 1958. Most of the correspondence is with the WEA, NEA, and other affiliated organizations. Much has to do with the process of running the organizations, solicitations for advice and information on teacher requirements, laws, and meetings.
Minutes originate from the numerous subcommittees of the STA, such as the Professional Rights and Responsibilities Advisory Council, Legislative Committee, Human Rights and Responsibilities Committee, Improvement of Instruction Committee, Personnel Sub-Committee, Special Task Force on Discipline, or Salary Committee. Many are also from the General Membership Committee, the large meeting of all members, and from the Executive Board Committee, the STA leadership meeting. The minutes are sometimes, though not always, sorted by committee. Much dates from the mid-1960s. This section also includes drafts of STA Proposals or Recommendations sent to the school board.
Financial information includes treasurers’ reports, financial records, payroll, and proposed budgets.
The Reports section includes education-related studies, many, but not all, of them conducted by the STA. These reports were a way to develop or to better support the STA position on specific issues. These also include information on school levies and reports on the activities of specific subcommittees. Reports are not in particular order, though some specific topics are separated out, and range from 1958 to 1966.
Ephemera and Miscellany includes speeches and writings, news releases, reports, and other ephemera. Speeches and writings are from STA, WEA, and NEA leadership, members of the Seattle School Board, the superintendent, politicians, and members of other teachers’ organizations. News releases relate to upcoming STA speakers, events, forums, and funding, and are in moderately chronological order. Reports include information on the activities of the Washington State legislature relating to education, as well as reports from the NEA, STA subcommittees, and other education groups in Seattle. News releases do not solely relate to the STA, but also to education in Seattle and the activities of other teachers’ organizations. Sources for clippings include the Seattle Times, The New Republic, and The Washington State School Directors Newsletter, among others. Newsletters originate from the STA, entitled various things such as “STA Flash,” “STA News,” “STA Newsletter,” or “STA Legislation News.” Some are intended to inform STA members of the organization’s activities and of their rights; others are intended to garner support from the local community. All newsletters date from the late 1950s and early 1960s. Ephemera includes advertisements, programs, brochures, and other documents, mostly not produced by the STA. Ephemera also includes near print items, that is, early drafts written by the STA for eventually published documents. Miscellany is primarily composed of permits and maps. The Subject Series is organized by topic, and topics are organized alphabetically. Much of the material in this subdivision is technically ephemera. It includes documents related to event planning, insurance, curriculum, salaries, and committee membership. ` This is followed by a section of Subcommittee Minutes. The final section consists of material relating to the WEA. At the same time, though, much of this material relates to the WEA and the STA; it is correspondence between the two organizations. This section also includes minutes, material from WEA conferences, and reports.
Records stored offsite; advance notice required for use.
Access restricted: For terms of access, contact Special Collections.
Donated by STA, 8/13/1970.
Seattle Education Association Records, 1958-1985 (Mss. Coll. No. 4217)
Seattle Teachers' Association (Seattle, Wash.)$vArchives; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); National Education Association of the United States; Teachers' unions$zWashington (State)$zSeattle
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Elementary and Secondary Education; Washington (State); Seattle
- SERIES I: CONSTITUTION AND BYLAWS, 1951-1967 (Box-folder 1/1-1/3)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1951-1961 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1959-1966 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1962-1967 (Box-folder 1/3)
- SERIES II: CORRESPONDENCE, 1954-1968 (Box-folder 1/4-5/30)
  - American Association of School Administrators, 1954-1960 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - American Association of School Administrators: Big Cities Leaders Conference, 1960 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1958 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1958 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Washington Education Association, 1958 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Incoming correspondence A-N, 1959 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Incoming correspondence O-Z, 1959 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1959 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 3), 1959 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 3), 1959 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 3 of 3), 1959 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - National Education Association, 1959 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Washington Education Association (part 1 of 2), 1959 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Washington Education Association (part 2 of 2), 1959 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Incoming correspondence A-M, 1960 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Incoming correspondence N-Z, 1960 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1960 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 4), 1960 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 4), 1960 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 3 of 4), 1960 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 4 of 4), 1960 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - National Education Association, 1960 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Washington Education Association (part 1 of 3), 1960 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Washington Education Association (part 2 of 3), 1960 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Washington Education Association (part 3 of 3), 1960 (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Incoming correspondence A-C, 1961 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Incoming correspondence D-N, 1961 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Incoming correspondence O-S, 1961 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Incoming correspondence T-Z, 1961 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1961 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 5), 1961 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 5), 1961 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 3 of 5), 1961 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 4 of 5), 1961 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 5 of 5), 1961 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - National Education Association, 1961 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Washington Education Association (part 1 of 4), 1961 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Washington Education Association (part 2 of 4), 1961 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Washington Education Association (part 3 of 4), 1961 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Washington Education Association (part 4 of 4), 1961 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Incoming correspondence A, 1962 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Incoming correspondence B-D, 1962 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Incoming correspondence E-J, 1962 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Incoming correspondence K-N, 1962 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Incoming correspondence O-S, 1962 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Incoming correspondence S-U, 1962 (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Incoming correspondence V-Z, 1962 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 2/23)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 3 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 4 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 5 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - National Education Association (part 1 of 2), 1962 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - National Education Association (part 2 of 2), 1962 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Washington Education Association (part 1 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Washington Education Association (part 2 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Washington Education Association (part 3 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Washington Education Association (part 4 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Washington Education Association (part 5 of 5), 1962 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Incoming correspondence A-B, 1963 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Incoming correspondence C-E, 1963 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Incoming correspondence F-K, 1963 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Incoming correspondence L-M, 1963 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Incoming correspondence N-R, 1963 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Incoming correspondence S, 1963 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Incoming correspondence T-Z, 1963 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 6), 1963 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 6), 1963 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 3 of 6), 1963 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 4 of 6), 1963 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 5 of 6), 1963 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 6 of 6), 1963 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - National Education Association (part 1 of 4), 1963 (Box-folder 3/22)
  - National Education Association (part 2 of 4), 1963 (Box-folder 3/23)
  - National Education Association (part 3 of 4), 1963 (Box-folder 3/24)
  - National Education Association (part 4 of 4), 1963 (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Washington Education Association (part 1 of 5), 1963 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Washington Education Association (part 2 of 5), 1963 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Washington Education Association (part 3 of 5), 1963 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Washington Education Association (part 4 of 5), 1963 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Washington Education Association (part 5 of 5), 1963 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Incoming correspondence A-F, 1964 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Incoming correspondence G-N, 1964 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Incoming correspondence O-R, 1964 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Incoming correspondence S, 1964 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Incoming correspondence T-Z, 1964 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 6), 1964 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 6), 1964 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 3 of 6), 1964 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 4 of 6), 1964 (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 5 of 6), 1964 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 6 of 6), 1964 (Box-folder 4/16)
  - National Education Association (part 1 of 2), 1964 (Box-folder 4/17)
  - National Education Association (part 2 of 2), 1964 (Box-folder 4/18)
  - Washington Education Association (part 1 of 5), 1964 (Box-folder 4/19)
  - Washington Education Association (part 2 of 5), 1964 (Box-folder 4/20)
  - Washington Education Association (part 3 of 5), 1964 (Box-folder 4/21)
  - Washington Education Association (part 4 of 5), 1964 (Box-folder 4/22)
  - Washington Education Association (part 5 of 5), 1964 (Box-folder 4/23)
  - Incoming correspondence A-N, 1965 (Box-folder 4/24)
  - Incoming correspondence O-R, 1965 (Box-folder 4/25)
  - Incoming correspondence S-Z, 1965 (Box-folder 4/26)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 5), 1965 (Box-folder 4/27)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 5), 1965 (Box-folder 4/28)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 3 of 5), 1965 (Box-folder 4/29)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 4 of 5), 1965 (Box-folder 4/30)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 5 of 5), 1965 (Box-folder 4/31)
  - National Education Association (part 1 of 2), 1965 (Box-folder 4/32)
  - National Education Association (part 2 of 2), 1965 (Box-folder 4/33)
  - Washington Education Association (part 1 of 2), 1965 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Washington Education Association (part 2 of 2), 1965 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Incoming correspondence A-F, 1966 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Incoming correspondence G-M, 1966 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Incoming correspondence N-R, 1966 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Incoming correspondence S-Z, 1966 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 6), 1966 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 6), 1966 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 3 of 6), 1966 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 4 of 6), 1966 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 5 of 6), 1966 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 6 of 6), 1966 (Box-folder 5/12)
  - National Education Association, 1966 (Box-folder 5/13)
  - Washington Education Association (part 1 of 2), 1966 (Box-folder 5/14)
  - Washington Education Association (part 2 of 2), 1966 (Box-folder 5/15)
  - Incoming correspondence A-F, 1967 (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Incoming correspondence G-N, 1967 (Box-folder 5/17)
  - Incoming correspondence O-R, 1967 (Box-folder 5/18)
  - Incoming correspondence S-Z, 1967 (Box-folder 5/19)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 3), 1967 (Box-folder 5/20)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 3), 1967 (Box-folder 5/21)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 3 of 3), 1967 (Box-folder 5/22)
  - National Education Association, 1967 (Box-folder 5/23)
  - Washington Education Association (part 1 of 2), 1967 (Box-folder 5/24)
  - Washington Education Association (part 2 of 2), 1967 (Box-folder 5/25)
  - Incoming correspondence A-L, 1968 (Box-folder 5/26)
  - Incoming correspondence M-Z, 1968 (Box-folder 5/27)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 1 of 2), 1968 (Box-folder 5/28)
  - Outgoing correspondence (part 2 of 2), 1968 (Box-folder 5/29)
  - Washington Education Association, 1968 (Box-folder 5/30)
- SERIES III: MEETING AGENDAS AND MINUTES, 1958-1968 (Box-folder 5/31-6/33)
  - General meetings, 1958-1961 (Box-folder 5/31)
  - General meetings, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 5/32)
  - General meetings, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 5/33)
  - General meetings: secretary's notes, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 5/34)
  - Representative Assembly, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 5/35)
  - Representative Assembly, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 5/36)
  - Executive Board, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Executive Board, 1960 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Executive Board, 1961 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Executive Board, 1962 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Executive Board, 1963 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Executive Board, 1964 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Executive Board, 1965 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Executive Board, 1966 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Executive Board, 1967 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Executive Board, 1968 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Executive Board: secretary's notes, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Committees, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Committees, 1961 (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Committees, 1962 (Box-folder 6/14)
  - Committees, 1963 (Box-folder 6/15)
  - Committees, 1964 (Box-folder 6/16)
  - Committees, 1965 (Box-folder 6/17)
  - Committees, 1966 (Box-folder 6/18)
  - Committees, 1967 (Box-folder 6/19)
  - Committees (part 1 of 2), 1968 (Box-folder 6/20)
  - Committees (part 2 of 2), 1968 (Box-folder 6/21)
  - Regional and sectional meetings, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 6/22)
  - Meetings with Superintendent of Schools, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 6/23)
  - Meetings with Superintendent of Schools, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 6/24)
  - Meetings with Superintendent of Schools, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 6/25)
  - Meetings with Superintendent of Schools, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 6/26)
  - Meetings of STA and Seattle School Board, 1959-1964 (Box-folder 6/27)
  - Seattle School District Employees' Insurance/Tax Sheltered Annuities Committee, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 6/28)
  - Seattle Alliance of Educators, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 6/29)
  - King County Coordinating Council, 1959-1965 (Box-folder 6/30)
  - Seattle School Board, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 6/31)